so this is Sanaya
45.1 it's called
ignorance it starts by the Buddha saying
buus ignorance is the Forerunner in the
entry upon upon UNH wholesome states
with shamelessness and fearlessness of
wrongdoing following along for an unwise person
following along for an unwise person
immersed in ignorance wrong view Springs
up for when a wrong view wrong intention
Springs up for when a wrong intention
wrong speech Springs up for when a wrong
speech wrong action Springs up for when
a wrong action wrong livelihood Springs
up for one of wrong livelihood wrong
effort Springs up for one of wrong
effort wrong recollection Springs up for
when a wrong recollection wrong
composure brings
up and the oppos it applies
for uh knowledge when a person has
knowledge instead of having ignorance
and then there's another
Su
56.7 that mentions what is that
ignorance and it
says uh a monk as the Buddha venerable
sir it is said ignorance ignorance what
is ignorance venerable sir and in what
way is one immersed in ignorance and the
Buddha says b not knowing suffering not
knowing the origin of suffering not
knowing the sensation of suffering not
knowing the way leading to the sensation
of suffering this is called ignorance
people and it is in this way that one is
immersed in
ignorance and then the
opposite uh what is a true knowledge
that would give rise as the Su I read
before says that would give rise to the
factors of the no way for path it says
knowledge of the origin of suffering
knowledge of the sensation of suffering
knowledge of the way leading to the
sensation of suffering this is called
true knowledge piku and it is in this
way that one has arrived at true knowledge
knowledge
so we were mainly thinking of focusing
on the aspect of right
speech and uh the reason that so is
important is because it's clearly saying
that wrong speech happens because of
wrong view it arises because of wrong
View and wrong view is there because of
ignorance because of not
understanding um the for Noble Truths
because of not being Noble disciples
so it's uh it's often the case that
people would think that wrong spe uh
right speech is just about adopting
certain external mannerisms and ways
of uh like we were discussing nonviolent
communication and patterns of expression
in that superficial sense
uh thinking that that in end of itself
constitute your own speech but right
speech yeah uh sorry right speech and
that you would avoid wrong speech just
simply by adhering to that which is
essentially just a a kind of
a virtue and Duty like external
observance that you adhere to
so yeah I thought of bringing up
starting with the suta because then we
can start to lay out how is it that but
simply on account of having wrong view
even if a person is trying to do their
best to speak a certain way uh they would
to speak a certain way uh they would
still not be partaking in that right
speech well white speech
fundamentally is about communicating
that which is wholesome or beneficial
for oneself and for others as
well and um that depends on having the
Right View so one can speak let's say
politely or be considerate and not in
any core sense um be violent or speak
harshly swearing and all the rest of it
which is definitely better than not
doing that but right speak spe as a
factor of the
path involves knowing what that path
is I mean it sounds obvious if you put
it like that but actually it's very easy
to um to to overlook
that so you know like UNH wholesome
speech Just For example like divisive
speech is UN wholesome right setting up
one person or one one group of people
against other group of people so
sometimes it's also better to just not
speak which does mean that you need to
restrain your speech but if
one does not see the value in Restraint
and you know you just speak whenever
there is the pressure to blur something
out then regardless of what you say it's
already an
awesome so we can go into that like like
like what are the factors from the point
of view of the Right View that makes
speech wholesome yeah because as you just said
wholesome yeah because as you just said
um it would be the main purpose of right
speech would be communicating it would
be wholesome if it's communicating the
Right View but to kind of play Devil's
Advocate you would see also in the suas
when the Buddha would have a
conversation with anyone he would say uh
in the beginning he would have
um the the p word it means like uh
amicable and pleasing or amicable and
Charming conversation with people and
then um obviously that part is not
like describing the suta because it's
essentially pointless MH but uh you
could argue well the Buddha was
sometimes talking about things that were
not explicitly uh the dhama from that point
explicitly uh the dhama from that point
of view right so um not like it was just
a entirely uh a dhh machine that only
uhhuh spoke uh no
so the the thing there as well is that
so the I guess the the the way we could
phrase the question is what is it that
makes speech wrong even if you are
adopting the external non nonviolent
communication and stuff what is it that
what what is it that would taint your
speech if you would act out of certain
pressures you say Buddha he didn't uh
use this polite forms of phrases of
conventions out of certain pressure
internal pressure because he felt uneasy
or I don't know fearful something like
that so that will determine basically
whether speech is H or
unome yeah one thing also like in the
line of what aan say is like if one hope
to get something out of what he's saying
whether he like pleasing someone in
order to kind of get approv
or get something later him or even like
if someone like about the D to look like
kind of intelligent like that I think
that yeah that is kind of a like the
intention is not so clear behind what
he's talking yeah that's a good example
because as you as you just said yes
fundamentally you um if the speech is
about the
dhama if it's rightly spoken from a mind
free from a virgin greed a virgin and
delusion it would be the best type of of
speech but a person could be speaking
about the dhama for all sorts of reasons
like monks could be speaking about the
dhama so as to inspire lay people so as
to get Don Nations and that would be a
kind of greed right there so one thing
to point out now that we're on on in
that area is that if you read the the
formula in the sutas it's always this
sort of templates it would explain for
example Right View as uh there's nothing
uh wrong view there's nothing given
there's no mother there's no father as
we discussed last time and then wrong
view uh wrong speech would be described
as so there's malicious speech uh lying
divisive speech um harsh speech but
fundamentally uh like just as with the
Right View it's not that those are only
the only wrong views that there exists
like there are myriads of of ways that
you can have wrong views that are not
explicitly described by that formula
uh same with the force ofas for example
it would say this is right recollection
but then the Buddha would talk about
other things that are also right
recollection but they're not mentioned
in that formula so the same applies for
the wrong speech it's not that only if
it's you know course harsh speech like
insulting someone it is wrong speech no
anything that is underling by greed
aversion and delusion is wrong
speech so it it might be the most
beautiful kind of a
poetic yeah and and about dhama totally
about dhama but if the person's mind is
contaminated with those three things
that speech is wrong speech even if like
he memorized the discourse from the
Buddha and he is giving it with a better
ination than the Buddha isn't with a
more uh pleasing kind of uh
verbalization and deliverance uh it's
it's still wrong because of the the Mind
State behind it so it's it's a
we did actually discuss that in the talk
about the what is wholesome and un
wholesome it's the the state of the Mind
behind anything that you do that really
determines what that uh what that thing
whether that thing is wholesome or un
wholesome and with the right view most
fundamentally what it comes down to is
seeing the signs of the Mind as would
describe the the fundamental thing that
a person without which a person cannot
get the right View
is seeing the signs of the mind
so uh I guess we could discuss that
later more in detail but in this context
what it would mean is being able to see
really what that GRE diversion and
delusion is in the first place so that
you know whether your speech is affected
with it or
not and uh if you don't see that if you
haven't seen the signs of the mind
because you haven't been uh virtuous
restrained and lived in solitude for
long enough then you won't even see the
background contamination of your speech
even though externally everyone
listening to you because they also don't
see as a said in order to know the mind
of another person you have to know your
own yes so they might be very inspired
by your speech and think that you know
you're you're a great calm and gentle
person but inside you can have lots of
um even if you don't have it right there
well you you can still be liable to
Greed Aion and delusion uh and to be
expressing that through your speech so
fundamentally it's kind of
circumstantial whether you are whether
you are at the moment not falling for it
and and that's the thing with the Right
View you would have you would knowingly
avoid wrong
speech whereas with the wrong view you
might be
externally doing what you think right
speech is but behind that you don't
actually notice that it's that there's
wrong so the right view is that
certainty that you can't be falling into
un
wholesome and not know it whereas with
the wrong view it can actually happen it
will most of the time happen yeah that
even though you think all this speech
action livelihood everything is fine
behind it there is all sorts of
bluring uh you know unalome motivations
there so yeah and the interesting thing
is like like the sign of the mind that
you just mentioned
that becomes clear when one dwells in
seclusion so it follows that if one is
truly concerned with gaining right
speech one has to basically start
avoiding other people physically and
start learning how to be alone in
seclusion in order to pick up that sign
of the minds to even know what right
speech is so you're not developing right
speech by surrounding yourself by a lot
of other people and and and learning
external skills and training yourself
that way because that is entirely
overlooking the rightness or the root of
the rightness of that speech yes so
because when you for example just
practice I I develop the skill of
talking to people by going out and uh
training myself in nonviolent
communication and uh using the right
Expressions not to upset people's
sensitivities well that might be good in
a worldly sense but uh none of that is
Reve ring you those intentions that
we're talking about like um because as
we said before intention is not like oh
um I'm saying this so as to not hurt not
hurt this person's feelings that's not
the that's just a rationalization that's
not the intention we're talking about
it's intention is as would say intention
of renunciation of intention of of
centrality or renunciation intention of
aversion or non aversion intention of
Cruelty or non- cruelty that is what in
is not like this explanation that you
come up with about why you're doing
something so that sort of intention
would only become apparent on account of
yeah seclusion so then if you have been
restrained and virtuous and blood and
seclusion and then for a while and then
you start seeing these signs of the mind
when you go back to talk to people you
would actually notice oh wait there's
this mental state here um that I would I
like in the past I might have had this
and I might have said well I'm saying
this because I'm trying to help this
person or because any sort of millions
explanations that you might might have
come up with secondarily to the fact
that no there is this form of greed
there MH and uh that that would only be
recognized as a as a result of you going
undergoing that training yeah not by
just speaking and speaking and speaking
like because none of that is question
questioning really what what those uh
underlying things are so yeah so this
also applies to people including
monastics living in community like if
all sorts of let's say interpersonal
difficulties arise then you can go and
sit in a circle and talk about your
feelings quote unquote but it's very
dubious whether that is going to go to
the heart of the matter in fact the more
time you spend in such um Mee things the
last time you have to dwell in seclusion
and pick up the sign of the mind which
is the factor for the Right View as we
just said and there's even a discourse
which appears at least three times in
different places in the nikayas so the
Buddha says like you know what are the
six factors for Harmony in a community
then it talks about uh like friendliness
like acts of friendliness by Body speech
and mind um keeping the training rules
for monastic sharing uh what has been
rightly turns to the point of the
contents of your arms ball and then it
says Factor number six he he has the
right View and he said that one is like
the the roof that holds the roof of a
bungalow that holds everything together
is the Pinnacle yeah yeah and that and
so that's precisely the whole point so
so if people have then let's say these
interpersonal difficulties rather than
assuming that by going into all that uh
and and sorting it out that that is
going to take away once and for all
those problems actually it is by gaining
the Right View that um that the pressure
that one would otherwise feel that one
acts out of um that under goes a radical
shift um and and so it's it's it's again
it's it's very questionable whether
people should come together and in a
sort of let's say group quasi
psychotherapeutical context that might
in a worldly sense people might think
that that's beneficial but um there's
absolutely no indication in the
discourses anywhere that that that
talking about those things is beneficial
yeah and and we actually discussed last
time that there was a suta where the
Buddha gives the instructions to the to
the new monks and one of them is that
they should speak little not that they
should be practicing uh you know yeah
put limits on your speech and then
restrain your sensus and become a forest
dweller and then uh go to monks who can
show you what is Right View which is
again the which is again the factor
there and so whatever difficulties you
might have uh with other people rather
than going into the content of that and
trying to figure out how to then live
harmoniously together basically you want
to adopt the perspective at the right
angle to all that yeah and and the uh
the the thing
with there's also this notion of like
the good friends or the Kalita uh-huh
and they would also kind of carry an
implication that it's just the people
who are nice to you that you have a nice
kind of relationship with in a kind of a
superficial sense that makes you feel
nice and wholesome but really when the
when the SS would Define what is kalana
the Buddha himself was defining what
that means it would describe how he
would be teaching the Dum for the
benefit of the world uh and that you
know it's something that people have to
train themselves in not like not like
someone you know to lean your head on or
something like that it's it's it's
something that it it needs to be someone
who has the right view who can point you
to what is good like that's why it's a
good friend not because of how they make
you feel in fact even the Buddha
said uh when when a Brahman went to ask
him is it that you always uh that you
would never say anything that would
displease someone because you claim to
be you know the foremost compassionate
being or something and then he said no
sometimes it's like uh he gave a simul
it's like when a when a baby swallows
something and it's about to choke then
you know he a per a normal person
sensible person would even like put
their their hands in their mouth and and
even take out blood if if if it's
necessary to save their life and he said
it's the same thing when he needs to you
know point out the the flaws in people's
views and stuff which is what but he was
doing most of the time and you know many
people might not feel like that's a
kalana a good friend because it's not
really making you feel very good most of
the time no uh and even to Ananda his
own disciple uh his his attendant there was
disciple uh his his attendant there was
that case where he was uh many mons
actually were gathering together for the
for the robe season festival and uh they
were gathering in these tents and stuff
and then the came and asked like why why
is it why there is does there seem to be
so many so many monks hanging around
here and uh I mean it was supposedly for
a good reason for sewing these robes and
stuff but the Buddha said well he
basically admonished all of them for not
being not living in solitude for
delighting in company and to Ananda his
own attendant he said like I won't treat
you like a like a Potter would treat his
his his you know valuable pots it's like
he will I will smash you and then the
the core is what will remain the core
that that is uh actually worthy so it's
that that wouldn't be considered a NOA
friend from the point of view of again
this nonviolent communication and and uh
like just don't hurt people's feelings
because that in and of itself is
bad uh like a good friend is the friend
who will stage an intervention for you
not the friend who's is giving you free
drugs yeah yeah which is
not it's basically not who seems like we
good friends yeah this like kind of
nonviolent communication that you point
out like not hurting people's feelings
like kind of imply the fact that oh
people other people can impact my
feeling and I can impact their feeling
so there is kind of this implication of
I'm responsible for them and you are
responsible for me and then we try to
kind of flow together like that but it's
kind of
yeah if each person like that's already
overlooking the responsibility that each
person has for suffering in the first
place MH each person it doesn't matter
how much you you insult someone
obviously doesn't mean you should do it
but if a person suffers that's because
they have they haven't understood uh the
way out of suffering so then by like
trying to create these safe spaces and
and trying to um think that that's what
creating a good Community is about like
just avoid offending people at all costs
you are kind of implying that oh
suffering is out there in the things
that other people do to you and not in
internally in your your own views
fundamentally yeah and another thing is
like it's important to point out that as
well that it's not bad in itself to try
to be gentle and and be polite because
um that's a that leads to more fluent
interaction between people fact in the
mundane sense but the problem is not
that the problem is when you prioritize
this and then because you automatically
forget that there is something more
important which is like right View and
then but the Buddha would be as as he
would say he would use gentle speech at
the right time and he would know the
right time for using Nao gentle speech
because he has a more fundamental
criteria than just how am I making
people feel yeah and that's why
sometimes he would be calling monks
inept man and stuff because that was the
right thing to do at that time so but I
think it did it only with monks though
like um yeah of course because people
who had uh already subscribed to the
training and basically accepted accepted
him as their guidance yeah that's right
so
um well actually he also when there were
these other Aesthetics of other other
sexy would also use the same term but uh
yeah the point is like um you wouldn't
if if you if you prioritize just that
superficial aspect you will become
complacent in thinking that on account
of this yeah you are factually avoiding
like some chunk of the amount of un
wholesome stuff but you would be
overlooking that there's way more work
to be done on the level of those
background intentions so that's really
the problem it's not that it's wrong
it's that people stop there and then
don't see that there's more more work to
be done and then the further work is the
meditation techniques and the focusing
and stuff so that I don't even then need
to be questioning my intentions and look
at at that level I just leave it there
leave leave the house half painted and
then go somewhere else in my in during
the meditation session yeah and uh
you're not really cultivating the stuff
that would make you the the type of
meditation that would make you discern
those UNH wholesome intentions when
they're there yeah that's what that was
actually the bud advice to his own son
rahula that's his whole discourse which
deals with speech and he says like you
know before you break the three yeah so
so before you break out into speech
consider is what I'm about to do
wholesome then while you are
talking and and so this is the Sati this
is the mindfulness or the recollection
and then while you are talking keep your
aim in mind like is this still wholesome
because it's very easy to start talking
because you see you might start talking
with a wholesome intention but you just
lose yourself in your own speech and
while you're talking it sort of deviates
and you end up almost doing the exact
opposite of what you want so you want to
be on the ball while speaking and then
afterwards perhaps when you are on your
own in seclusion you can still look back
and cons consider does that speech now
actually awesome or not and and see the
that wouldn't be possible that what you
just said that the intention changes
from an um from from holen to unhen if
it were in the content of what you're
saying it's really the Mind changes it's
inclination towards the
situation some form of greed that wasn't
there arises but you might be talking
about the same topic saying the same
words that you might have otherwise said
nothing really changed on that on that
level but you internally now have a
different uh impulse a different there's
something different that's pushing you
now to to say these same things
and that's what makes it wrong now so uh
yeah you it it's always has to be
recognized the as the buha said action
is
intention so anything UNH wholesome a
Chet is a word anything UNH wholesome
has to be that not just like you know he
didn't say action is the the movements
you make with your hands and the sounds
that come from your mouth no it's the
intention so if you purify that internal
level by recognizing it first and
foremost then you wouldn't have to worry
about what you say externally you purify
the source of the river in order for the
you know later yeah uh current to be
clean you don't like start from the
ground up that's just wasted wasting
effort and you're never really going to
get anywhere so um that's essentially
what's happening most of the time like
you would be uh by trying to control
your expression and stuff and thinking
okay this is it you don't look you don't
look any further M and um that's another
thing with uh
with uh
the like when people have for example
Restless mental States and worry and a
lot of you know hectic uh hectic
thoughts and stuff they would think well
I I need to now use a concentration
technique to calm myself down but
really if
you were actually restraining your
speech rightly first of all your actions
then then your speech you would see you
you refrain from all this useless talk
the Buddha defined the 10 uh topics that
are not worthy of discussion uh you know
talk about politics food
sensuality uh Kings
clothes uh money uh relatives relatives
uh
Gossip it's called like talk of the well
like when people would go to the well
and they would talk and talk of the well
so um you refrain from that stuff then
you won't have in the first place these
truly overwhelming uh mental States when you
overwhelming uh mental States when you
go into when you're alone uh so then so
rather than this is so rather than
trying to solve the problem afterwards
when the mind is is already spinning out
of control you are saying that you find
yourself in such a state one pillar
there is the unrestrained speech from
the past yeah so instead of trying to
clean something that don't get it dirty
in the first place yeah instead of
needing to clean clean after the fact so
um you would see that then the
Purity like it would become something
that uh you no longer have to be hoping
for or anticipating like you know how
people would say well today my Med was
not good and it's almost like well
that's that's that's just something
random like was a bad day yeah yeah but
no absolutely not like Purity is
entirely in your hands if you didn't do
anything un wholesome you can't be
impure even if you want to like during
if during the whole day you didn't
engage in any un wholesome intentions
and right now you're not engaging in any
un wholesome intentions it's impossible
to have a bad uh day in terms of your of
your dhama practice yeah so so it
doesn't mean it will be pleasant but
again um that's not the criteria that's
not the Criterion the Criterion is am I
giving in a virgin when there is
displeasure and uh that would give rise
to a different kind of Peace than the
peace that comes when sometimes your
meditation technique Works M it's a
different
that yeah earlier you you you played
devil's advocate for minutes and brought
up the let's let's say friendly and
amiable talk that the Buddha sometimes
has you know when people come to see him
um and we should distinguish that from
the from the gossip or the or or the
let's say Idol talk which is clearly UNH
wholesome and it occurs to me that
gossip in particular is a good example
to review
inauthenticity like inauthenticity can
be described as just uncritically taking
over the views and the opinions and or
the or the opinions and the beliefs
while so without questioning whether
they're true you take them over and then
you assume that they are just
disconnected ideas latent in the back of
your mind and that they do not affect
how you act by body and by speech but
but it's not like that and then and then
furthermore having those ideas all all
already and seeing them as fairly
harmless and innocent you then pass them
on to others um and so that that that's
what gossip does so it it it has that
similar structure you you hear something
you don't even be bothered whether it's
correct or not so you don't see that you
have a responsibility for what you
accept and what you reject and then on
top of that you pass it on to others
which is also within the spere of your
responsibility so to to fully refrain
from just passing something on without
being reasonably clear whether it's
correct or not that's already on the
level of speech moving in in the
direction of authenticity but even then
if you are more more or less clear
whether something is correct it still
doesn't necessarily mean that you should
therefore pass it on to others so
whether you then break out into speech
so to speak then that involves a whole
other layer of cons considerations and
you said like yeah what what is UNH
wholesome is to speak when there's
pressure and that does imply The View
that you can release the mental pressure
by breaking out into speech whereas
actually there are two different domains
so if someone recognizes that you cannot
actually relieve that restlessness or
that worry or that doubt or any kind of
mental agitation by just talking about
it that that or your emotions like you
said like having this uh talking about
your feelings with other people as if
that releases it and makes you yeah
because feel better yeah because I I
think it would be good to to to briefly
clear that
because the way that the dharm is
presented nowadays has become so
intertwined with the host of Let's say
more psychotherapeutical ideas that the
whole idea that to engage on that level
and to just speak or learn how to speak
about that that that is somehow
beneficial I think needs a fair amount
of qualification
yeah I was just going to say yesterday L
and I were talking about how it's like
it it almost feels like there's no kind
of like it almost feels like things can
just kind of flow out you know like I'm
not responsible for it it just yeah was
in my mind and that's how that's how
that's how you need to see like that is
a sign that there's development to be to
be had because you would see okay um if
there is that sense of connection means
I'm not taking responsibility by default
for what there there has to be some sort
of buffer like before you say things uh
and and that would be cultivated on
account of the restrained like if you
have been restrained beforehand your
mind inclines towards um as but it would
say you inclin the mind in a different
directions so then even way before you
actually start falling into these traps
you would see yourself going that
direction so it only ends up in that
case where it feels like whether it be
by speech body body speech or mind it
only gets to this point where where it
feels like the UN wholesome is almost
like Happening by itself because
beforehand you were overlooking the
little stepbystep progression towards
that fullon it's like a snowball and
then you you don't stop it at the right
time it's just it just keeps going so
but that's connected to the other thing
you were saying now that um the the
gossip and stuff you wouldn't be able to
tell like if you had to determine what
is wholesome and UNH wholesome but
having some sort of list of to analyze
like topic okay so this is about this
and this and it's 3 p.m. right now and
he like that's impossible to actually
keep up it the practice needs to be to
the point where um it does you don't
even need to reflect like you already
know before you even say it it's beyond
doubt that's that's what the Dumber
should be so it's only when you take it
on the level of that pressure as you
mentioned that you would start to
see it it doesn't matter even I don't
even need to worry about the the content
of of what I'm saying it won't be gossip
if I'm not talking out of pressure and
then any useless topics you're like by
default it won't even occur to you to
talk about this because you're not
that's that sort of stuff that truly
serves no purpose cannot come out unless
you are giving it to pressure yeah so
you take that that as the standard and
then you ask yourself well if I don't
say this this right now is my mind going
to start complaining about me not saying
like that pressure starts starts to
build up then you can see oh if I speak
I'm actually kind of um furthering the
the agitation of this wild animal and
then you just keep going and uh then you
are surprised when you try to stop it
and you can't well it's because you
you've been letting it run wild so
that's where you that's where the
training is and seeing that when am I
speaking out of pressure and then you
you start to see the the mouth as a kind
of Gateway that it doesn't matter how
much like like a dam that's holding
water it doesn't matter how big the
pressure gets to let the water out you
are the one who has to actually open the
dam and let it flow it can't happen by
itself so that's where you were saying
like it's three different domains it
doesn't matter what you're thinking
about how much you want to say it if you
don't if you succeed in not saying it
that's that's all that matters and so
yeah but we should also now add that it
that we cannot fully go to the other
side of the extreme and start
determining to not say anything at all
yeah yeah so I'm I'm saying like I don't
I don't mean uh not talking I mean when
you see that there is the pressure yes
and then you refrain from that in that
like uh with that background recognition
that's already of actually that it's
good to bring that up because the uh
there's even the Buddha forbade this vow
of silence which is ironically the
principle with which like I think most
meditation Retreats operate that you
can't you can't speak at all or or like
just um one or two words per day or
something because um the reason why that's why
because um the reason why that's why
that's wrong is because you're not even
trading yourself so that when you get
out of there you actually see what what
so what are the UN wholesome intentions
behind my speech that were making me
stressed agitated and and lustful when I
wasn't in this Retreat you you didn't
learn anything about this yeah and and
people yeah and and but people will be
able like when they hear this I'm pretty
sure they will be able to relate that
like it's in a sense it's much easier to
just determine I'm not going to say
anything for 10 days rather than leave
that 10% window where it's still okay to
say something because that now forces
you to question is it really necessary
for me to say this that's actually much
more unpleasant yeah and then that will
force you to learn what is wholesome and
what is UN wholesome and you you you
won't be trying to Riggle out of the
problem so easily and uh because you
can't it's it's factually at some point
you will have to speak and uh that goes
with everything the in general the the
practic the sorts of practices that
people take on for running away from
things and and Bur ing their head in the
sand for for a while and that's the kind
of piece it gives you but you haven't
discerned why when your head was out of
the sand why things were a problem yeah
so you're not really um well you're not
fixing the problem that that the Buddha
talked about like that ignorance not
knowing suffering not knowing the escape
from suffering on account of which all
of these wrong things come to be wrong
speech wrong action wrong livelihood so
that is that can only be done
by as we've been saying so many times uh
the the intention behind your action
being clear about it and seeing that
seeing that as a training like day and
night you you are aware of whether your
actions by as you said in the
Rah you would you would be reflecting
before I do it is this rooted and
pressure while I'm doing it is this
rooted pressure after I did it is a
really pressure and then that is
actually teaching you like because you
learn from your
mistakes by not taking this blind vow
silence and then you look back and you
reflect oh wait on that occasion I have
a feeling that that was that was not
wholesome and then you see why MH was it
because because of some external
situation or was it because at that
moment I had this mental state of greed
of versin so that's what you Rec collect
the mental state and then
you will actually remember that mental
state because you know in the past like
you you can look back and see what are
the motivations even though it was a
past event you can see yourself like um
why you did something on that that level
that matters that level of intention and
then when it comes up again in the
future you have a reference point oh
wait this is the same thing that I that
I did the other day and then you started
you start seeing it
um again in the mental inter interal
level where the the level of intention
on account of which actual wrong speech
uh can can come to be so and that like
oh I did this the oh this is the same
kind of situation as the other day that
doesn't even mean like it's the same
from the outside like it could be
completely different like the image is
just totally different like one you're
alone one you're like surrounded by
people just like the the actual content
of what's happening is not yeah yeah
yeah so it it could be absolutely
anything like because the I mean the
things you say for example I was going
to bring that up uh the example of
mahaka when he would be you know he
called Ananda he called him a boy and
and that I mean he's the Buddha's
attendant and and that was that sort of
language would have been or that sort of
attitude would have probably been
considered like how can an AR hunt say
something like that to someone and then
uh on the other occasion like when they
were on the council he forced Ana to
confess uh a bunch of offenses to see
them as wrongdoings and so in general he
was just this kind of um like he refused
to um to instruct the monks because he
said these days monks are full of evil
wishes and and they don't they don't
actually care about the dhama so you
know he that could be by people who
think the the the speeches about as you
said the content to what you say that
could be considered as a as a form of
wrong speech but because there would
have not been any sort of
um predilection for great version
delusion behind him saying that M which
only he could know MH then uh or another
person like who who also has a right
view then uh there was there wasn't any
problem with it but then if you don't
take responsibility and you think oh
well look that mon speaks like that so I
can also do it do it but no because
again you would think you would still be
putting it in the content and you
wouldn't be taking responsibility for
seeing this mind what what state is it
in right now yeah and uh yeah different
people after you understand the way our
suffering and stuff would have different
still different uh Tendencies and ways
of of uh talking or whatever so um yeah
some people might be more naturally uh
you know Meek and and gently spoken and
other people might be a little bit you
know more
abrasive and and that's not that's that
that doesn't really uh mean anything
fundamentally on on the on the internal
level as long as there are obvious
things that you cannot do like you can't
go insulting people because I mean that
is what is defined literally as wrong
speech in the in in the formula that I
just mentioned like that is the obvious
stuff that if you do it you're
automatically falling to wrong speech
also um another thing I thought was
important to bring up um it's also
mentioned in the SAS many times that you
shouldn't exalt yourself and uh put
others down and I think that is that's
also included in the in the context of
of right speech sometimes because
uh so the thing with that is usually the
assumption is so criticism is bad
essentially like even if you should be
focusing on bringing people up instead
of um putting them down but but the
thing is like it doesn't say it says you
refrain from exalting yourself and
putting others down it doesn't say you
ensure that you put yourself down and
exalt others no because that that would be a
others no because that that would be a
sort of self-denigration which is also
an aesome yeah or or not even fullon
self-denigration like trying to to
almost artificially uh kind of focus on the
artificially uh kind of focus on the
good qualities like someone's someone's
promoting wrong view but you see oh you
try to find like the positive aspect of
it so as to you know not not put
yourself up in yeah sometimes with
somebody's Behavior you can do that if
you are about to do something un
wholesome you can do that but there are
indeed other discourses where the the
Buddha even says how should one monk
admonish another right yeah no but and
and then it it should be like beneficial
the timing should be right with a mind
of friendliness and and so on so so the
whole idea that to not exalt oneself
does not mean that one cannot um let's
say um rebuke or or criticize someone
else that actually that doesn't follow
yeah yeah no but I wasn't referring to
like a person you're actually talking to
I was referring to in the sense of views
like when when the Buddha for example
said um uh you shouldn't be he actually
defined it in this
this maaya he said how is it that a
person falls into this denigration and
self-exaltation and how is it that they
only speak dhma MH because uh that is
like people might think again that it's
just by criticizing other views
you are somehow being considered
arrogant that you need to kind of allow
space for other people to be right as
well but the thing is the the thing is
um as the Buddha said how do you how do
you avoid that you don't avoid it by not
Point by not pointing out that there is
right and wrong which is again kind of
an easy way out of the situation and
does doesn't fix it at all it's it's
by instead of saying it talk in terms of
me like I am wrong you are wrong I
refuted your argument you're you're oh I
see what you mean yes then you you
instead say whoever is practicing like
this they are attached to being that's
the literal uh way the Buddha explained
it Whoever has this sort of practice
they're attached to being they don't see
the way out out of craving um they they
they have wrong view whoever practices
this way they have right view they see
the way craving instead of saying uh you
know these people are are our hunts and
these people are are total penous
understand so you don't you don't focus
on the person specifically you focus on
The View you focus on the views so you
criticize and that's what the Buddha was
doing he was criticizing the views that
people had not like personally attacking
people and that's really personally
attacking or personally exalting himself
like to make himself feel um you know
make himself a appear in that kind of
personal sense like there's some sort of
uh contest between us and I'm trying to
come out on top that's really when you
end up exalting yourself and and U
denigrating others and how would you
tell well a very practical senses U
practical test that you can do is like
if you are criticizing somebody's views
but then do you feel like you actually
now have a personal problem with that
person as well like if you had to talk
to to meet that person whose views
you're criticizing would you have some
sort of internal animosity or would you
be able to treat them totally like a
like a normal person on a kind of um you
know that the the the usual polite way
that you would treat somebody else or
would you be like that's that idiot that
believes this so that's how you would
know if your speech is really rooted in
yeah and this goes back to the question
of to the discussion of patience that we
had like County like like the highest
discipline or the highest austerity but
it's also paired with gentleness often
like that's the aim of athetics so you
have to endure still somebody else's
wrong view but then are you s are you
going to challenge somebody even if
those views are effectively wrong are
you going to challenge that because it's
more pleasing for you to not have to
suffer somebody else's wrong view or is
the D just about stating what is Right
View yeah are you averse to the pleasure
of seeing that someone has a wrong View
and then you're trying to call it out
that's when you will automatically end
up debating on that personal level and
the suta describes actually that sort of
a back and forth thing it says like U uh
I am right you are wrong what you said
before what you said after you said
before what you said before you said
after I totally contradicted everything
you say go back your you know yeah try
to rescue your teach try to rescue your
your teachers if you can so that's a
very you see that that's not something
that can happen by accident like just
because you said well this sort of
practice is wrong that's like a fullon
you attacking somebody because you have
a you have you are upset internally and
and uh that's a very different thing
because the Buddha spent all the time
almost uh like half of the the stuff he
was saying was pointing at wrong view
the other half was once that's done then
you point out what's right so you can't
uh just decide that
you can't point out what's wrong because
I mean he himself said not pointing out
Nama as n dama is like it's it's a it's
a it's a form of wrongdoing like or not
recognizing n dama as n dama yeah like
refusing to recognize it so that you can
keep that sense of superficial Harmony
yeah that's actually only if you have
wrong view would you be able to to
engage in such a thing because it's
authenticity it's like bad bad faith and
this is where the timing then becomes
important like you might recognize a
wrong view as wrong but it not but it
does not necessarily mean that this is
now the right time to address it so so
you need to take your own let's say uh
mood or State of Mind into account but
you also need to see whether the other
person is to some extent receptive to
what you are about to say so you might
have to endure for quite a while
somebody's wrong View and then find a
proper occasion to say look actually the
whole thing is otherwise and that is a
skill but that only comes into play once
you realize a wrong view as wrong view
which is only possible when the view is
right yeah and and and like you you
would um like I just said you're just
meeting the person in a totally mundane
sense um it's not a discussion about
dhma but you know that this person has
wrong view you wouldn't like hey by the
way yeah that's that's not because
that's not the right time so that's as a
Buddha said you need to know the right
time so but in that time that you're not
actually talking about it if you see
yourself being averse to the person on
that personal level um then that's
clearly a problem now and then if you
still decide to point out the wrong view
even even though let's say technically
you're right but you're doing it now and
you you can't wait for the moment when
you can finally just that's again GRE
you see yourself then you catch yourself
and that's wrong so again that would
always be on that internal level not
about what you're going to say to the
person even yeah